Laure Zanna

Dept. of Physics, University of Oxford phone: +44 (0)1865 272925

Parks Road, Clarendon Laboratory email: laure.zanna@physics.ox.ac.uk

Oxford, OX1 3PU, United Kingdom url: laurezanna.github.io

ORCID: 0000-0002-8472-4828 **Google Scholar:** https://goo.gl/79xWUF

Research Interests: ocean and climate dynamics; predictability and prediction of the climate system and uncertainty quantification; and the (stochastic) parameterization of ocean turbulence. *Tools*: Advanced analytical, numerical and statistical methods, a hierarchy of numerical models, and analysis of available observations.

Education

2009 PhD, **Harvard University**, Earth & Planetary Sciences. Subject: Climate Dynamics.

Title: Predictability and variability of the Atlantic ocean circulation. Adviser: Eli Tziperman.

2003 MSc, Weizmann Institute of Science, Environmental Sciences.

2001 BSc, **Tel Aviv University**, Atmospheric Physics, *Magna Cum Laude*.

Professional Appointments

Oct 2011-present: Associate Professor (previously University Lecturer), University of Oxford, Department of Physics

(tenured in July 2016).

From Sep 2018: David Richards' Fellow and Tutor in Physics, Wadham College.

Oct 2011-2018: Fellow, St Cross College.

Oct 2014-2017: Lecturer in Physics, Christ Church College.

Sep 2017-2018: Visiting Research Scholar, Princeton, AOS and GFDL, USA.

Apr 2009-Oct 2011: **James Martin Research Fellow**, Oxford Martin School; **Junior Research Fellow**, Balliol College; **Postdoctoral Research Associate**, Atmospheric, Oceanic & Planetary Physics, University of Oxford.

Oct 2003-Mar 2009: Graduate Research Assistant, Earth & Planetary Sciences, Harvard University.

Awards and Fellowships

2017-2018: Visiting Research Scientist Fellowship, Princeton, AOS and GFDL, USA.

2009-2012: **Oxford Martin School Fellowship**, University of Oxford.

2009-2012: **Balliol College Junior Research Fellowship**, University of Oxford.

2008: Outstanding Student Paper Award, American Geophysical Union, Fall Meeting.

2005, 2006, 2007: Bertram J. Cohn Fellowship for Environmental Studies, Harvard University.

2006: Young Scientist Outstanding Paper Award, European Geosciences Union, General Assembly.

2005-2008: 3 × Certificate of Distinction in Undergraduate Teaching, Harvard University.

2003: **Beni Landau Fellowship**, Weizmann Institute of Science.

2001: **Magna Cum Laude**, Tel Aviv University.

Funding

2017-2022: **NERC - Large Grant**, Oxford PI. Transient tracer-based Investigation of Circulation and Thermal Ocean Change (TICTOC), £3,342,981.

2017-2019: **Royal Society, International Exchanges Scheme**, PI. Quantifying the Variability of Tracer Transport across the Gulf Stream. £11,830.00.

2017-2020: NERC, Co-I. Addressing the Grand Challenge of regional sea level change prediction (UKFAFMIP), £584,852.

2014-2018: NERC - Directed, Co-I. Summer: Testing Influences and Mechanisms for Europe (SummerTIME), £764, 189.

2014-2017: **NERC**, PI. Modelling the Ocean Circulation with Random Numbers, £301, 109.

Laure Zanna, CV 2/5

2012-2016: **NERC - Directed**, Co-I. Representing uncertainty in ocean observations and the ocean model, for coupled ensemble data assimilation and ensemble extended-range prediction, £378,722.

2013-2017: **NOAA- Earth System Science Program**, Co-PI. Variability, stochastic dynamics, and compensating model errors of the Atlantic Meridional Ocean Circulation in coupled IPCC models, \$287,032.

2011-2014: **John Fell OUP Fund**, PI. Dynamical Impacts of Unresolved Ocean Processes in Climate Models: Lessons from Stochastic Physics, £98,538.

2015-2016: **Met Office- Oxford Academic Partnership**, Undergraduate Research Experience Placement. PI, 2016: two proposals funded; 2015: one proposal funded, each for £2,000.

Teaching & Mentoring

Teaching Activities

2010-present: Lecturer and College Tutor, University of Oxford

2013-present: Lecturer, Physics of the Oceans & Atmospheres (undergrad).

2014-present: Lecturer, Climate Dynamics and Variability (grad).

2016-present: Lecturer, Advanced Math and Numerical Methods (grad).

2010-present: *College Tutor* (undergrad): Mechanics & Special Relativity, Circuit Theory & Electromagnetism, Flows, Fluctuations & Complexity (Nonlinear Dynamics, Chaos, Stochastic Processes, Biophysics).

2009: Invited Lecturer.

Joint UW-MIT-Bjerknes Advanced Climate Dynamics Course, Bergen, Norway.

MIT Course on Adjoint methods: from large scale optimization to climate modeling.

2004-2008: *Teaching Fellow*, **Harvard University**: Climate & Physical Oceanography (undergrad/grad); The Atmosphere (undergrad); Ordinary and Partial Differential Equations (undergrad/grad); Nonlinear Dynamical Systems (undergrad/grad).

1999-2002: Special Educator, Teacher and Tutor, Balfour High School, Mathematics.

2015, 2016: *Organizer and Speaker*, **University of Oxford**, Atmospheric Physics Research Experience Day for NERC DTP incoming graduate students.

Supervision ($^+$ = co-advised)

Postdoctoral Scholars:

May 2015-: Chris O'Reilley (+ with T. Woollings)

2016-2017: Joakim Kjellsson

2015-2017: Stephan Juricke (+ with T. Palmer)

2015-2016: Markus Huber (funded by a S-NSF fellowship).

2014-2015: James Anstey, now permanent researcher at CCCma

2012-2015: Fenwick Cooper (+ with T. Palmer), now postdoc at Oxford

2011-2013: Mirek Andrejczuk (* with T. Palmer), now permanent researcher at UK-Met Office

2011-2013: Luca Porta Mana, now researcher at Perimeter Institute

PhD/DPhil Students:

Mar 2016-: Thomas Bolton

Oct 2013-: Robert Fraser

2013-2017: Tomos David (* with D. Marshall)

2011-2015: Ben Bronselaer, now postdoc at GFDL/Princeton

MPhys Students = senior thesis: (*=won a prize for best project in Atmospheric, Oceanic and Planetary Physics). 2016-2017: Jonny Ison; Kirill Mikhaylov. 2014-2015: Thomas Bolton*. 2013-2014: Andrew Bailey*; Michael Walker*. 2013: Tomos David. 2012: Shaomin Cai. 2011: Brodie Pearson.

Summer Students: Alex Gyoffry, Arnaud de Larturiere, Benjamin Huddart, Twm Jonathan, Andrey Orkney.

Laure Zanna, CV 3/5

College Graduate Supervision (St Cross and Christ Church): I act or acted as College supervisor for about 15 students in Physics, Earth Sciences, Engineering, Materials, Genomic Medicine & Statistics, Musculoskeletal Sciences, Physiology, Anatomy & Genetics, Organic Chemistry, Life Sciences, Healthcare Innovation, Bioscience.

Additional Service and Examination

Examiner for 1 external and 2 internal PhD defence, and 1 MRes defence.

Internal Examiner/Graduate Committee for 8 first-year and 6 second-year students.

Physics Teaching Faculty, **Invigilator**, Physics of the Oceans & Atmospheres, 2015.

Physics Teaching Faculty, Assessor, Flows, Fluctuations & Complexity, 2016-present.

Judge for students presentations: Ocean Modeling 2011, 2012, 2014; AGU Ocean Sciences and Fall Meetings various dates 2012-2017; AMS AOFD 2017.

Presentations (as first author only)

Invited Departmental Seminars (52 since 2009):

- **2018**: Caltech, Flatiron Institute/Simons Foundation, UW, NYU/Courant (APM), *Upcoming:* Harvard, U. Chicago, UCSD/Scripps, NCAR.
- **2017**: Lamont Doherty Earth Observatory LDEO (colloquium), GFDL, Columbia University/LDEO (Ocean and Climate), NYU/Courant (CAOS), George Mason University, U. of Edinburgh, U. of Reading.
- 2016: ANU, U. Tasmania, U. of Copenhagen, Imperial College London (Physics), Leeds.
- **2014**: UCLA, Caltech, Scripps Institute of Oceanography, British Antarctic Survey, UCL, NOC/Southampton, Weizmann Institute of Science, Tel Aviv University.
- **2013**: Imperial College London (Math), Harvard, MIT, U. of Cambridge (DAMTP), Hebrew University of Jerusalem, Weizmann Institute of Science, Reading.
- 2012: LPO/IFREMER Brest; New York University; U. of Hamburg/Max Planck Institute of Meteorology.
- before 2012: Imperial College London (Physics); U. of Reading; U. of Oxford; U. Cambridge (Earth Sciences); European Centre for Medium-Range Weather Forecast; Proudman Oceanographic Laboratory, Liverpool; U. of East Anglia; National Oceanography Centre, Southampton; MIT; Columbia University/LDEO; Princeton/GFDL; Tel Aviv University; Beer Sheva University.

Invited Workshops and Conferences (31 Invited since 2009):

Upcoming 2018-2019: Caltech - ESM 2.0 Workshop, AIMS Conference on Dynamical Systems (Taipei), US AMOC/RAPID (Miami), Equadiff 2019 minisymposium.

- **2018**: AGU Ocean Sciences (Portland), Understanding the relationship between coastal sea level and large-scale ocean circulation (ISSI, Bern), Oceans in Weather and Climate (Exeter, OiWC2018).
- **2017**: ECMWF Annual Seminar on Ensemble Prediction, Intrinsic & Forced Ocean Variability Workshop, Max Planck Institute for the Physics of Complex Systems, Banff International Research Station for Mathematical Innovation and Discovery, MFO Oberwolfach Research Institute for Mathematics.
- 2016: Data Analysis and Modeling in Earth Sciences, Uncertainty Quantification SIAM.
- **2015**: Future Lagrangian Ocean Modeling, ICIAM Beijing, Turbulence Days, Europe Dynamics Days, Workshop on Stochastic Physics in Climate, Theoretical Advances in Planetary Flow and Climate Dynamics, Met Office Academic Partnership, Ice2Ice (keynote).
- **2014**: AGU Fall Meeting, ClimathNet (plenary).
- 2013: AGU Fall Meeting, IMA Workshop on Stochastic Modeling of the Oceans and Atmosphere.
- **2012**: AGU Fall Meeting, ESA workshop on model uncertainty.
- **before 2012**: Workshop on Representing Model Uncertainty in Weather and Climate Prediction (2011), EGU General Assembly (2009), Advanced Climate Dynamics Course (2009).
- Selected Contributed Presentations (27 since 2009): Model Hierarchies Workshop, Princeton 2016; AGU Ocean Sciences 2018, 2016, 2014, 2012; Workshop on Energy transfers in the atmosphere and in the ocean 2016, 2015; RAPID/ US AMOC annual meeting 2015, 2013; Latsis Symposium on Climate Dynamics 2014; AGU Fall Meeting 2013, 2012; American Met. Soc. AOFD 2013, 2017; APS General Meeting 2013.

Laure Zanna, CV 4/5

Selected Academic Service

External Committees

2018-: Lorenz Committee Member, American Geophysical Union.

2014-: International Scientific Council Member, European Institute for Marine Studies (IUEM), Brest.

2011-2016: Peer Review College Member, NERC.

2016: Scoping Group on the Role of Southern Ocean in the Earth System, NERC.

2015-2016: **Belmont Forum and JPI Climate, Panel of Experts**, "Climate predictability and inter-regional linkages".

2017-2018: Schmidt Fellowship Panel Member, Schmidt Foundation, Earth Sciences Division.

Convener and Organizer

2018: **Session Co-organizer:** APS - GPC Focus Session, Los Angeles, *Multi-Scale Flows and Pathways in the Climate System*.

2017: Invited Organizer, Workshop on Transport in Unsteady Flows, Banff International Research Station.

2016: Invited Convener, Ocean Section IUGG Conference on Mathematical Geophysics.

2012, 2014: Session Co-organizer: AGU Ocean Sciences, Salt Lake City 2012, Oceanic Uptake of heat and greenhouse gases: dynamic and thermodynamic controls and inferences from tracers; AGU Ocean Sciences, Hawaii, 2014 North Atlantic ocean dynamics: from natural fluctuations to externally forced response.

2012: Session Co-chair: IUGG, Mathematical Geosciences 2012. Ocean processes: from small scale to global circulation

Additional Service

Reviewer: *Proposals*: NSF, NOAA, NERC, ISF, BSF, KAUST/CRG, Irish Research Council. *Articles*: J. of Climate, Nature, Science, GRL, Clim. Dyn., Ocean Modelling, J. Phys. Ocean., J. of Physics A, ERL, Q. J. Roy. Met. Soc., Phil. Trans. of the Royal Society. *Books*: SIAM, Cambridge University Press.

Organizer, Atmospheric, Oceanic and Planetary Seminar Series, Nov 2012-Aug 2016; Physical Oceanography & Climate Meetings, 2010-2011.

Physics, **Personnel Committee**, 2012- present; **Parking Committee**, 2017- present.

Oxford Colleges: **Governing body**, Balliol College, 2009-2011; **Executive Committee**, Balliol College, 2010-2011; **Governing body**, St Cross College, 2011-present, **Fellowship Committee**, St Cross College, 2014-present.

Selected Outreach

Wadham College, Foundation Fellows Event, 2017: Sea Level Rise.

Royal Society, Physics Alumni Event, 2015: Oceans in Climate Change.

Oxford Physics Society, 2016: Physics of Climate Change.

Oxford Physics Alumni Weekend, 2013: Ocean Physics.

Since 1992 (in France, Israel, USA and UK): Various activities and tutoring for middle- and high-school students with learning disabilities and from disadvantaged backgrounds.

Publication List

List: http://www.earth.ox.ac.uk/~laurez/files/publications.pdf

Google Scholar: https://goo.gl/79xWUFs

Download Published Manuscripts: http://www.earth.ox.ac.uk/~laurez/

Laure Zanna, CV 5/5

Academic References

Eli Tziperman

McCoy Prof. of Oceanography & Applied Physics Harvard University Dept. of Earth and Planetary Sciences, & School of Engineering and Applied Sciences Cambridge, MA 02138, USA (+1) 617-384-8381 eli@seas.harvard.edu

David Marshall

Prof. of Physical Oceanography University of Oxford AOPP, Dept. of Physics Clarendon Laboratory Oxford, OX1 3PU, UK (+44) 1865-272099 david.marshall@physics.ox.ac.uk

Jonathan Gregory

Prof. NCAS-Climate University of Reading Meteorology Building, Reading, RG6 6BB, UK (+44) 118 378-5602 j.m.gregory@reading.ac.uk

Teaching Reference

Jonathan Jones

Professor of Atomic and Laser Physics Head of Physics Teaching Faculty University of Oxford Atomic and Laser, Dept. of Physics Clarendon Laboratory Oxford, OX1 3PU, UK (+44) 1865 272247 Jonathan.Jones@qubit.org